<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A solemn exhortation made and published to the several churches of Christ within this province of Lancaster, for the excitation of all persons therein to the practise of their duties, requisite to the effectual carrying on of church-discipline; and in it the edification of our churches, and the reformation of religion. / By the provincial synod assembled at Preston, Feb. 7. 1648.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E542_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865173</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">164930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 164930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E542[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A solemn exhortation made and published to the several churches of Christ within this province of Lancaster, for the excitation of all persons therein to the practise of their duties, requisite to the effectual carrying on of church-discipline; and in it the edification of our churches, and the reformation of religion. / By the provincial synod assembled at Preston, Feb. 7. 1648.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Luke Fawne, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Parrot in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C. XLIX [1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:164930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Solemn Exhortation made and publiſhed to the ſeveral Churches of Chriſt within this PROVINCE of LANCASTER, FOR The <hi>Excitation</hi> of all perſons therein to the practiſe of their Duties, requiſite to the effectual carrying on of Church-Diſcipline; and in it the Edification of our Churches, and the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion.</p>
            <p>BY THE Provincial Synod aſſembled at <hi>Preston,</hi> Feb. 7. 1648.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for LUKE FAWNE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the <hi>Parrot</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. M.DC.XLIX.</p>
            <p>
               <add>feb 1648</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:164930:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:164930:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative header consisting of a French fleur-de-lis flanked by a Tudor rose and a Scottish thistle</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>A Solemn Exhortation made and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to the ſeveral Churches of Chriſt within this Province of Lancaſter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Government of the Church of Chriſt, which he himſelf inſtituted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this Province lately reſtored to the hands of thoſe his Officers unto whom he himſelf committed it: He (who is the Head of the Church, to whom God the Father hath given all power in Heaven and in Earth,) having ſtirred up, and ſtood by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and pious Parliament, (whoſe Acts will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned,) to wreſt it out of the hands of thoſe that u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped, depraved, and miſ-adminiſtred it, and, with the Advice of the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it (vindicated and purged from the former deprave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and confirmed with their civil Sanction,) to thoſe his ſervants, unto whom by his Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he had aſſigned it. The faithful Execution of this Government now reſts upon the charge of thoſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers with whom it is ſo, both by divine Commiſſion, and humane Injunction, entruſted; and the diligent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:164930:3"/>improvement of it to ſpiritual advantage remains upon the care of thoſe Churches and Church members over whom it is placed, and to whoſe benefit it is appointed to be ſubſervient; and if either the Execution of the one, or the improvement of the other, be ſlacked, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, of it will faile, and great will be the fail thereof, We of this Synod, called by the aforeſaid Authorities, opening a way to the Churches, whereunto we ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appertain, to deſign us to the preſent inſpection of this large Aſſociation of Churches for their edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; having ſet our ſelves to finde out, and purſue what (within the extent of our power) may be conducible thereunto, have quickly apprehended the promoting of the aforeſaid due execution, and improvement of Church Government, to be mainly neceſſary to that end; and not only taking notice of, but laying to heart the flow proceeding of it among us, more eſpecially in ſome places, and more particularly in ſome duties, have thought meet amongſt other means for the putting on thereof, to addreſs our ſelves by way of exhortation to all our Churches, and in them to all our Brethren, both publike Officers, and other Members, beſeeching the God of all Grace through Jeſus Chriſt, That this our ſervice may be acceptable and profitable to them, being ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>The matter (dearly beloved in our Lord) of Church Diſcipline, which we perſwade, were it either Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or of a temporal concernment, we ſhould have paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it over in ſilence at this time; but when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that it is one of thoſe Commandments which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, before his aſcending up to Heaven through the Holy Ghoſt, gave unto the Apoſtles whom he had choſen, and whom he charged to teach all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:164930:3"/>made his Diſciples to obſerve all things whatſoever he had commanded them; and that it hath the Church of God, and the ſouls of men purchaſed by his precious blood for its object; The reſtoring and preſerving of the purity of Chriſts Ordinances, the verity of his Doctrine, the orderlineſs of mens Conventions, the Peace and Union of Chriſtian Brethren, and Churches in Judgment, heart and practiſe for its end, and that ignorance, error, and iniquity, are the enemies againſt which it draweth forth, and weildeth its weapons; we cannot but ſpeak, and yet withal judge a little ſpeaking for this to them to whom we ſpeak may ſuffice.</p>
            <p>The miſerable diſorders, errors, and offences, which like a flood have broken out, continued, and riſen to ſo great a height among us, to the high diſhonor of the Name of God, the great hinderance and ſhame of the Goſpel, and the trampling of the holy things, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pearls thereof, under the feet of dogs and ſwine, the ſubverſion of many fouls, the vexation of others, the disturbance of our Churches peace, and the errecting of many walls of partition betwixt brethren, the decay and diſcouragement of the power of godlineſs, the opening of the reproachful mouths of the enemies of Religion, the advancement of Satans ſeat amongſt us, the pulling downe and continuing of many nationall Judgments, and the rendring of Reformation ſo extremely difficult. Theſe theſe, O Brethren, are the deplorable fruits of the want of this Diſcipline; which but to mention may make all pious cars to tingle: what then may the ſeeing and enduring of them ſo long move in our hearas? And how great a guilt ſhall we incur, if we ſhall be now wanting in our places, either to the ſetting up, or dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent practiſe of this Diſcipline? And here as we cannot
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:164930:4"/>excuſe our ſelves in our own conſciences, ſo we deſire not to conceale that in the late Prelaticall Uſurpation; we are conſcious to our ſelves of departing from our duty, in complyance with the miſ-proccedings thereof: we judge our ſelves for it, and we do earneſtly deſire, that our failings herein may be ſo far from becoming a preſident for future, either to our ſelves or others, that the remembrance thereof may be to both, for time to come, a Caveat and an incentive to obfirmed fidelity and diligence in all our diſciplinary duties; and that whatſoever ſort of men may come hereafter to carry themſelves in way, either in neutrality, diſcountenance, prohibition, or opposition to us therein, we may yet acquit our ſelves in the ſame. We would not have to he forgotten how long the work of the Reformation of this Church, in point of Diſcipline, hath ſtayed, and ſtuck behind thoſe of Doctrine and Worſhip, which hath been our great ſtain and tryall: With what prayers, tears, ſolicitations and teſtimonies, by preaching, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, practiſing, and ſuffering, our Predeceſſors, and we have ſtriven for the effecting of it? What expectations and hopes of late have bin conceived of it? What under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings gone about, and adventures made for it? What delays and obſtructions have been interpoſed? How much, and many ways Satan and wicked men have ſtood againſt and retarded it? What conteſtations and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts have been encountred? What coſts, not onely of wealth, but of blood, expended for the attainment of it? What a publique, ſolemn, and ſoule-binding Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and Oath, hath been takin by us, and moſt people in this Nation, ſincerely, really and conſtantly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor the ſame? By what ſlow ſteps, through the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and hazardous oppoſitions made againſt it, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:164930:4"/>of other urgent affairs, and the intermixture of humane frailties, the Parliament, the Aſſembly of Divines, and the ſeveral Church Aſſemblies, in their reſpective endeavors about it, have proceeded? And how, in, and above all, the moſt mighty hand of God hath been exalted, and his unſearchable wiſdom, and rich mercy magnified in, not onely the redemption of our lives, liberties and eſtates, from the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the full ſubduing of them once, and again, before the Lord, and before his people, but the bringing forth out of all thoſe perplexed, dangerous, difficult, and croſs occurrences of great advantage to us, as in many other reſpects, ſo eſpecially in the eſtabliſhing of Church-Government in that good meaſure in which it is ſetled: The progreſs whereof in this Province, we have much cauſe to admire, and ſtudy thankfulneſs for: And we confeſs the greateſt defects that now remain concerning it, are in the practiſe of it, which is our part; and that the unfitneſs, unſetledneſs, averſeneſs, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſneſs of mens ſpirits in relation to it, is now the great obſtruction at which it ſticks: And we may be jealous, leſt as the want of love to the Truth hath, through the juſt Judgment of God, been a wide inlet in many places to damnable Hereſies, ſo the want of a heart in us to uſe this price in our hand of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power, may lay us open to deſtructive diſorder. We obſerve alſo, That as mans corruption and Satans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice concurred to hinder Church Diſcipline while the work of diſcovering, clearing up, and publique autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing of the rule was in hand, by raiſing and keeping up of differences in judgment, with hot and doubtful diſputes concerning it, unworthy aſperſions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt caſt upon it, anticipations of mature directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:164930:5"/>of authority about it by ſome brethrens rending from our Churches, and ſetting up ways of Diſcipinle diſſonant to it, private, politique deſignings under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of it, a common hatred to Reformation, and ſtrictneſs impoſed by it, diſaffection and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to it by many in places of Power; expectation and endeavors for a legal Toleration, and an aſſuming of liberty in Religion for the preſent, the fruitful mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all Atheiſm, Error, falſe Religion, and Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſo do they ſtill concur by the ſame arts and means, and that with a higher hand, to hinder the putting of it in practiſe: ſo that by the ſhort experience we have had, and the preſent face of things, we may very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably make account to meet with yet as much, yea more difficulty in the carrying on of this Diſcipline, then was found in the eſtabliſhing of it; which ſome men, whoſe counſel is fleſh and blood, diſcerning, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps take occaſion thence to languiſh, in their active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or wholy to refrain from acting, or to ſtand off from joyning in it, and happily to blame the godly forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of others: but we wiſh ſuch men better counſellers, and hope all thoſe who are acted by principles of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and ſpiritual intereſt, will, from the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch difficulty, collect an obligation to more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and thence addreſs themſelves with greater zeal, courage, and reſolution to the work.</p>
            <p>All theſe mighty engagements, and impulſives, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and beloved, being with ſerious and right Chriſtian conſideration weighed, we beſeech, and exhort you, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, That the Government and Diſcipline of the Church, ordained by Chriſt, and ſet forth ſummarily by authority in the Ordinance of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:164930:5"/>Parliament of 29. Auguſt 1648. be preſently, faithfully, conſtantly, and impartially put in practiſe, in all Church aſſemblies, by all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ruling Elders, and other Chriſtians, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Power, or Commandment, delivered to them in the Word of God reſpectively, with all other known duties of Religion coming with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the cognizance of the ſaid Government; and in particular as conducing, or neceſſarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant thereunto theſe following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That in ſuch Congregations as are not provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of ruling Elders, and may afford any number of perſons duly qualified for that Office, the Miniſter and People do without delay or excuſe, proceed with due ſolemnity to elect ſuch Elders; and that the perſons ſo elected take upon them the ſaid function, as thereunto called of God; and that the Claſſical Presbytery, to which that Congregation appertained, or, if that be not, the Miniſters, and others, nominated by Ordinance of Parliament of 2. Octob. 1646. as ſit to be of that Claſſis, proceed to conſtitute that congregational El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip, to which the ſaid perſons are ſo choſen; and the Elderſhip ſo conſtituted to addreſs themſelves to the Execution of the Diſcipline in their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with all diligence, and to aſſociate themſelves as they have opportunity to the Claſſical Presbytery, which they belong unto.</p>
            <p>That the Miniſters of the Goſpel give themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to prayer, and to the Miniſtry of the Word; that they ſtudy to ſhew themſelves approved to God, workmen that need not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the Word of Truth; that they be eminently and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary holy, and blameleſs in their converſation; that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:164930:6"/>they be quick ſightedly watchful againſt the ſpringing and ſpreading of Errors, and the breaking out of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions within their flocks, and that they labor to inſtruct by way of catechiſing all the young, and weak in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg within the ſame.</p>
            <p>That the Miniſters and Elders ſet themſelves dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to the overſight of their Congregations, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern into, and help them in their knowledg, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al eſtate, and to diſcover, direct, and correct their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, therein paſſing over none that profeſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity within their bounds, uncaſt our of the Church, and endeavoring the recovery of thoſe that are caſt out; That they conſtantly meet in publique, that they may be ready for the addreſſes of the people, and to conſult on, and apply ſuch means as may be effectual for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the congregation, or any member thereof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That they rule with diligence, and impartiality in the application, or releaſement of Church cenſures, as the condition of any ſhall require: That they punctually obſerve the meetings of the aſſociated Presbyteries, Claſſical and Provincial; that in matters too hard for their ſingle Elderſhips, or wherein they are appealed from, they may reap the benefit of joint counſel, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and prayer, and mutually afford the ſame, and that none of them detract, grow weary, or ſuffer themſelves to be diverted from frequenting ſuch aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, although the affairs of Church-diſcipline, being ſo newly entred upon, be for the preſent ſomewhat extraordinarily preſſing.</p>
            <p>The Claſſical Presbyteries (being that one ſpecial work of theirs is to ſuperintend them that have the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of others) are beſought to take ſpecial care, that the Miniſters, and ruling Elders, within their reſpective
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:164930:6"/>Diviſions, be ſufficient for their callings, induſtrious in the execution thereof, and unblameable in their walking; in which reſpects their accuteſt vigilancy is required, that the unworthy be timely prevented, the negligent, or offenſive regulated, and the unreclaimable ejected.</p>
            <p>All Chriſtians whatſoever are exhorted, That they beware of giving any offence to any, either by manifeſt ſin, or by the appearance of evil, remembering that double heavy woe, which in the ſentence of our bleſſed Saviour offences bring, to wit, one to the world, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the offence giver. That they carefully avoid all raſh, or groundleſs taking of offence againſt any perſon, or practiſe, not judging upon in evident caſes, as being bound out from it by a double Law of Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: And here, whereas there are ſaid to be ſome that murmur againſt certain of the Communicants, in the ſeveral Congregations, as if they were viſibly unworthy of the Lords Supper, We deſire that ſuch complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers would rather apply themſelves to their duty of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate admonition, and publique information, and proof thereof before the Elderſhips reſpectively, and not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably charge, either an unworthineſs upon a party, or a miſ-adminiſtration upon an Elderſhip before a due eviction thereof be made.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as imputations of infufficiency and ſcandalouſneſs are in general expreſſions, and in private talk, caſt upon ſome Church-Officers; we earneſtly pray, that there may be either an orderly complaint, proſecution, and proof made of ſuch imputations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Presbytery whereto any ſuch Officer belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, or a forbearing of ſuch ſmitings with the tongue. Furthermore, Chriſtians are exhorted, That what er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:164930:7"/>or offences, they plainly diſcern in any brother, they take notice of them, not to hate, diſdain, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid, or preſently to withdraw brotherly reſpect, and ſociety from him for the ſame, much leſs to whiſper, or publiſh ſuch things, when, where, or to whom there is no warrant, to the defamation, or exaſperating of the party, and the multiplying of offences, but to exerciſe pity, and endeavors of recovery towards him; if the matter be a ſmaller failing, or but an infirmity, to inſtruct, and perſwade him, and patiently to bear, expecting his amendment: if the matter be of an higher nature, and ſcandalous indeed, let every one take heed of winking at, or being wanting in his place, to the removing of the Scandal, and make conſcience to apply himſelf according to the rule of Chriſt, by a ſet, ſolemn, and opportune admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition in private to the lapſed party, withal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, fidelity, meekneſs, and love, accounting it a happy work to gain a fallen brother, and that this private admonition is ordinarily the firſt ſtep to the proceſs of Church-Diſcipline. If upon it the parties repentance be not diſcerned, follow our Saviours rule to the next ſtep, take along with you to the perſon, one or two faithful brethren, That they may be both witneſſes and aſſiſtants to a ſecond admonition: If neither in this courſe a good effect appear in him, omit not that third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy preſcribed by Chriſt, of telling it to the Church, but go and acquaint the Elderſhip with thy brothers treſpaſs, thy paſt proceedings for his reclaiming, and the ſucceſſeſneſs thereof, which laſt remedy is to be made uſe of forthwith in all publique<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known, or openly divulged ſcandals; and both in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:164930:7"/>caſe of ſuch publiſhed Scandals, and in thoſe more private, ſo perſiſted in againſt brotherly admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as is aforeſaid; we exhort every perſon that is offended, or knoweth, and can teſtifie the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact, That he willingly appear and witneſs the ſame before the Elderſhip; all which is to be done by every one reſpectively, as he tendereth the ſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the offender, the putting away of the evil from the Church, the vindication of that worthy Name of Chriſt, by which we are all called, and the purity of his Ordinances, and that he himſelf may not be a partaker of other mens ſins: In this courſe of admonition, and proſecution before the Elderſhip, let none out of private ſpleen revive the memory of old, and forgotten offences; which not only tract of time, but the real Reformation of the party, unto the full ſatisfaction of the godly, and ſilencing of the world, may have buried: And let every one that is overtaken with a fault be ready to receive, ſubmit to, accept of, and improve to his good the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of any Church-Officer or Brother given him, as an act of conſcience, and love in his Brother, and as to him ſelf a kindneſs or excellent oyl to heal him.</p>
            <p>Alſo we exhort all Chriſtians cordially to eſteem and affect, diligently to attend upon, really to ſubject themſelves to, and profitably to uſe what Diſcipline is but the conſervatory or incloſure of, to wit the publique and private Ordinances of the Goſpel, as the Word, the Sacraments, Prayer, and the reſt: And in regard of that great neglect, we obſerve in many places by many, of that ſoul-feaſting Ordinance, the Lords Supper, which was ſo dearly bequeathed by Chriſt immediatly before his death unto his Church; We exhort, that no perſon of age, that names himſelf by the Name of Chriſt, would
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:164930:8"/>ordinarily abſent, or wretchleſly deprive himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but that he labour for knowledg to enable him to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelf for faith, and for a good conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and man; and that he be diligent in the uſe of all publique and private means to attain the ſame, and particularly that he ſubmit to be catechiſed by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and tried, and approved by the Elderſhip. And whereas ſome that come not to the Lords Supper, nor offer themſelves to the Elderſhip to be admitted to it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine as if they were kept back by them, they are exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to pretend themſelves to be debarred by them whereas they never tendered themſelves to be received. And whereas others that abſent themſelves, except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the manner of admiſſion, by approving themſelves to the Elderſhip in point of knowledg and converſation, ſuch ſhould religiouſly weigh upon what binding grounds the Elderſhip requires the ſaid ſatisfaction, and to endeavour themſelves, either to receive reſolution of the Elderſhip, or Miniſter, for their inſiſting on ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, or to yield reſolution to them for their refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to give it; and if that way they gain not acceſs to the Ordinance, rather to appeal to the Claſſical, and thence to the Provincial Aſſembly, in caſe they find themſelves agrieved, then to ſit down without uſing what means they are afforded to gain participation in ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and precious an Ordinance.</p>
            <p>All Governors of Families are exhorted to ſee to the godly ordering of their houſholds, to obſerve conſtantly, and to bring all under their charge unto Family Duties of Religion, as Prayer, reading the Word, repeating, and taking account of Sermons, eſpecially on the Lords Day, ſinging of Pſalms, catechiſing them, and bringing them to be catechiſed by the Miniſter, that they may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:164930:8"/>come to, and grow up in the knowledg and obedience of the truth, neceſſary to their Salvation; and ſo to reſtrain them from wickedneſs, and lead them to godlineſs, both by their own example, and by their authority, that (as much as in them lies) the Church, or any of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren be not offended with any of them; and their eternal happineſs may be procured.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſuch as keep Schools for the education of youth, are exhorted to train up their youth in divine literature, and to diſcipline them to eſchew vice, and practice piety, themſelves alſo exerciſing duties of Religion in their Schools, and being every way exemplary in good to them; and that in allowing times of recreation, they, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Directory, leave the obſerving of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, and exchange them for other convenient times.</p>
            <p>And we exhort, That if any Brethren amongſt us, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any thing diſſent from the preſent conſtitution of Church Government, or take offence at any practiſe in any of our Churches, or Members, they would beware of running into, or continuing in Schiſm thereupon, but walk by the ſame rule with us, ſo far as there is an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in judgment betwixt us, and endeavor to receive or give ſatisfaction wherein there is any practical difference, and take heed of violating their own declared principles, concerning continuing, or withdrawing of Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let all Chriſtians chiefly ſtudy, ſtrive for, and exerciſe the power of godlineſs, whereto Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ſerveth as an handmaid, and whereof viſible confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity is but the outward ſhape; and let the maineſt of their care be employed in the getting and keeping of faith and a good conſcience, the materials of that power of godlineſs; and ſeeing moſt perillous times are come
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:164930:9"/>upon us, wherein it is oppoſed and aſſaulted by all ways, both of ſubtilty and power: We earneſtly exhort and warn you all, that with exquiſite heed and reſolute ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſs ye diſcern and reſiſt all thoſe that ſhall ſeek to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you, either into error, or diviſion, contrary to that ſound doctrine, and ſafe fellowſhip, which ye have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced in our Churches; that with accurate circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection ye keep your ſelves from the common and raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſins of theſe times; that ye ſtand faſt to our ſolemn League and Covenant, in all the branches of it, and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in thoſe that contain the great, and much hazarded, publique Intereſts of Religion, Civil Government, and Brotherly Union, not ſuffering your ſelves to be drawn aſide to any new inventions, to the ſubverting of any of them: And that ye walk in the old path, and good way of the infallible Scriptures, and avoyd ſuch courſes, as have but the warrant of pretended good intentions, ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſity, or miſ-interpreted providence coyned for them; And if it be the Will of God, That ye muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for not ſaying a confederacy to ſuch ways, or for well doing, be not afraid of mens terror, neither be troubled, nor aſhamed, but ſanctifie the Lord God in your hearts, rejoyce, count your ſelves happy, glorifie God on this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, and commit the keeping of your ſouls to him in well-doing, as unto a faithful Creator.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Hyet,</hi> Moderator.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Johnſon,</hi> Aſſeſſor.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Edward Gee,</hi> Scribe.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
